All right. Hello and welcome. It is
April 8th, 2025 and we're in active
guest stream 101.1 with Nelson Jafari
and Julie Lee. So, thank you both for
joining and looking forward to this
presentation and discussion.
Well, Dario, thank you so much for
having us here. Uh, it's really great
pleasure. Uh, what I'm going to do is
I'll have I have few slides for you.
I'll I'll present my slides and it's a
open discussion. So, please stop me
whenever you have questions and um
that's about it. So, let me start again.
My name is Mosen
Jafari. I am professor at Rothgre
University of Engineering.
uh this work uh we have been working in
this area for the last I would say four
to five years and this is a joint work
with professor Angia Mata from poly
techchnical
Milana there are four PhD students
currently working on this actually one
of them Yui Hong the last one he
graduated uh about a year ago but the
rest are in the program they are they
are working in the
program Um so what I'm going to do um
well again it it it took us a while to
understand active inferencing. I am
myself coming from automation
background. I've half computer science
half engineering. So I'm very familiar
with the modeling with the stochastic
systems and so on so forth. But
definitely uh in terms of active
influencing the uh it was a little bit
different for for me to to get
acquainted with but uh that's why it
took a while to to basically understand
the terms the jarens and the underlying
assumptions and so on but we feel that
we are quite u comfortable with the with
the theory and the framework.
um our background is engineering. So we
like to see that we can apply active
influencing to engineering systems. So
that is really the main theme, the main
thrust of our our group's work and for
that reason we are looking at u you know
large complex human machine systems
where you have physical systems,
machinery, buildings, communities and so
on and at the same time you have humans.
So there are both aspects of it and
these are large systems. So one example
here is like a a building community or a
smart community. I'm sure many of us
have heard about this where you have
some buildings. Each building has zones
and and then you have the community
which has many buildings in it and these
communities are part of a larger network
sometimes called distribution network.
If you are looking at from energy
perspective then you can connect to the
power grid or any other type of network.
So there are different you know there's
a hierarchy of hierarchy of different
layers in the system and it's quite
complex. It's the way that information
is
being passed up and down and being
processed. There are many issues in
terms of privacy,
confidentiality, abstract abstraction of
information and so on. So that's one
example and I'm going to talk more about
this as we move on. Another example is
in the top in the production systems the
production systems manufacturing systems
are usually complex system. There are
many many uh stations, robotics and you
name it. And in in there are many
examples where you have hundreds or
thousands of this machinery in the same
same um you know same uh area and of
course these systems interact with the
environment with outside and there are
lots of complex interactions inside the
system. Another system of the same
complexity that involves again machinery
and human is is roadways. You know
navigation in the roadways. You have
cars and and these days we have mixed
traffic. You have smart cars, you have
not so smart cars and and of course the
interaction between all this you know
vehicles in the system uh in terms of
navigation is a quite complex problem.
Um along the same line you can look at
the simpler systems but you can look at
very complex dynamics in the system. I'm
borrowing this picture from from the
literature but basically think about
this table with a robot that tries to
push the ball but the table has a
complex dynamics in terms of tilting in
terms of friction on the table. So
exactly what you do and what you see may
not be exactly what you are trying to
do. And this is another type of system
that we are we are trying to to look
into and study. And again if time allows
we will discuss
this. Let me just go back a little bit.
Um the whole idea of looking at the
generative modeling is not new for us.
uh I would say uh about 15 to 20 years
ago I I have I I did some work in this
in this topic again for large complex
systems. The whole problem there is that
to build this um like in this case this
automotive models for uh distributed
systems and our work research was to
build algorithms where you can actually
generate this the automato model for the
whole system in some smart in some
automated way. So this is a this is
something that we have been doing for
for some time and it did not directly
relate to active inferencing but again
the whole idea of creating generative
models for the purpose of creating
perception of how the system works has
been there in the p you know in in in
the past. This is another example of a
manufacturing system. Actually this is a
real manufacturing system where the idea
is you want to build this graph model on
the right hand side which happens to be
a pri petriet
uh and you want to be able to develop
this petriet based on the information
that you know you collect from the
system and again this could be a very
complex system and the problem of
interest here becomes okay how do I
create this graph model that describes
the logic of how the system works in
some smart uh automated way. This is
another example we did in the past. Uh
here you have a simple chemical process.
You are receiving uh sensory information
from the process and the idea is to
build a state transition model. Um,
Daniel, I know that one of, you know, in
your email to me, you asked the
question, how do you incorporate the
sensory information to building your
your your models? And actually, this is
one example of it that you directly use
the sensory data to uh create the um
create the transition state transition
model and these state transition models
basically describe the the behavior of
the process. Again, I'm not going to go
into detail of it, but what I'm trying
to the point I'm trying to make is that,
you know, the whole idea of generative
modeling and automation has been around
for some time, but not within the
context of active
inferencing. Um, so when we are looking
at this type of you know human machine
systems, we are talking about really
complexity in terms of the physical
systems. There is a lot of physics uh
behind the systems and of course there
is human and all the you know
complexities that comes with the human
behavior. Usually with the system state
spaces are very large and especially if
you shuffle the states together because
of the dependencies then the problem
becomes quite complex.
Um in many cases uh you have hybrid
systems in in terms of some of the
activities functions are time based. So
you have to have a continuous model for
it and some of the activities are event
based. So you have time based and event
based dynamics and that definitely makes
the problem more interesting and more
complex.
Um again we have many sources of
uncertaintities in these systems.
Usually what you do and this is this
pract this has been the practice in the
past and now is to create some layer by
layer de composition of this type of
systems in terms of states variables
outcomes data and so on. And of course
nowadays we have all the issues with the
data confidentiality and privacy and so
on that you need to consider in these
systems. So before we get into too much
of detail let's just look at a very
simple case. Suppose I have this
building and suppose that this building
has only a single zone and what I'm
trying to do is I want to basically
control the the temperature in this
building. So the or in this zone. So the
problem of interest here is how can I
build an active inference model to do
this. So I want to create an agent that
can actually control this this zone. And
for that reason what you need to do is
you need to create of course your hidden
states, your controls, actions, your
observations, outcomes and preferences.
All of it together. I'm not going to go
to details of it, but in a zone like
this, it makes a lot of sense to assume
that the occupancy level in the zone is
hidden from the controller because
either you have to have very
sophisticated sensory network in the
zone to know exactly how many people are
there because as you know the occupancy
impacts the temperature and humidity in
the in the zone and also infiltration,
external infiltration. If you somebody
keeps the window open or the door open,
it will definitely impact the the
temperature inside the zone. So these
could be you can consider these as
hidden variables. And in terms of
actions, excuse me, in terms of actions,
the amount of air that you supply to the
zone as well as the um um the the the
flow rate and the temperature both in
terms of rate and the temperature is
something that you can control. So and
and for the observations suppose that
you have the thermostat or some sort of
sensor that you can see the temperature
in the zone or average temperature in
the zone and let's show it by 5T. So
basically I have my hidden states I have
my outcomes or 5T and I have my actions.
Now within this context you can actually
build u an active continuous active
inference model for this without getting
in too much into the dynamics of the of
the system. Actually this is quite
complex dynamics in terms of you know
the thermal flow but by using the active
inference you basically avoid that and
you use this probabistic model to
control to basically build your model.
I'm not going to go through the details
of this but you can actually do it. You
can create your your um the elements of
your active inferencing and uh and one
thing that I like to to mention is that
let me just go through this and
basically explain the details of it. uh
we said that the temperature in the zone
is five but we define a G function that
describes the outcome in terms of the
hidden states and actions very normal
very regular in active influencing
literature right and we are going to
assume that it is gian with some sort of
a noise
level now from thermodynamics we know
that we can describe the temperature in
the zone through this time series
function and it Just happens that here
that this time series function is a
function of control actions as well as
hidden states that makes life much
easier. So that basically describes your
G function through which you can
describe your outcomes in terms of the
hidden states and actions.
uh you can continue the formulation and
active inferencing on this uh formulate
your uh variational free energy and one
idea that you may want to have here is
that you define a target. The target is
very interesting here because as a as a
owner of the zone, you may actually set
some uh the band gap for the
temperature. And what you want this uh
active inferencing agent to to make sure
that the temperature stays within within
this target band gap. So it is very
doable and again that is what I'm
showing here. And of course you can use
your uh
uh variational free energy. You can look
at the gradients in terms of the
inferencing and in terms of control. So
again I'm not going to go through this
details. We can always come back to this
if you have questions later on. But I'm
just following the normal literature in
active inferencing to do this
formulation.
Of course, you can generalize this to
much more complex and more general. And
here I have some general formulation of
it in terms of different variables that
has to go to this type of continuous
active inferencing function and and def
and how you define the targets because
usually the target for an active
inferencing agent in this type of
systems comes from a higher level. And
the way this target is defined depends
on the dynamics at at the higher level
and the lower level. And definition of
this type of target is very interesting
in this type of system. That is one of
the areas that right now we are doing
some research on to see how we can
actually do that type of formulation and
build this hierarchal model in this
context. Um again I'm not I'm just not
going to go through the details. Let me
move to another layer. Suppose that you
have a community now. So within the
community, you have different agents.
Each agent could be a zone or a
building. I just showed you how you can
do the zone. But you can extend it to a
building assuming that the zones are
independent. If the zones are dependent,
of course, it just makes your model much
more complex, but it's still very
doable. Now when you are looking at the
from the community level of course there
are lots of confidentiality and the
privacy issues and the active
influencing agents at the lower level
are not going to give all the detailed
information about their what's going on
there to the higher level. So there is
some abstraction of information that
will go from the lower level to the
higher level and that is exactly what we
are trying to model in this case. Again
let's move on with uh and if you have
questions we can always come back to the
to the um form the detailed formulation
but but without any going through
details you can actually define the
hidden states in some abstract level you
can define observations in some abstract
level you can define actions in sub
abstract level at the community layer
remember you have the building you have
the zone You have the building, you have
community and as you move on the
abstraction level becomes more and more
and you can form all the matrices and
all the relationship. At the community
level we are assuming that your active
inference model is discrete. So at the
zone level we are trying to control
temperature. Clearly it is time based
whereas in the in the community level we
are trying to basically set some
commands between the or define some
commands to the lower levels. So we deal
with it in discrete way. Let me just add
here that if if I may go back to here
when you are looking at this higher
level community layer or level you are
dealing with the distribution network
much you know another higher level I am
assuming that the distribution layer is
going to set some targets and also it is
going to give some information to the
community for example market price and
or the day head plan which is very usual
in the sense that you define
your schedule of how you are going to
consume energy for tomorrow. So this is
the target that the community level
active influence has to has to respect.
So you you can set all these targets at
different levels and our formulation
again we are going through the same
active influencing formulation. You can
use markup blankets, you can use
different forms of it to to do the
formulation. Here I'm just showing you
some simple examples and um again you
will have my slides but active
inferencing is doing amazing. It is at
the community level it is able to to
follow the target very well. It is able
to minimize the pricing system and also
the use of I am assuming that your
community for example has solar panels
and energy storage and it tries to
optimize the usage of all this together.
So that is really very exciting and very
interesting to see that without truly
understanding the inner dynamics of
these complex systems, I can actually
employ active inferencing to come out
with u with the
controls which otherwise you have to
either use some reinforcemental learning
or some exact models which sometimes is
not even possible because the flow of
information and the flow of the physical
elements such as you know thermal flow
and all that is is very
complex. So um let's move on. Uh now
this brings us to another example in the
production system and I'll tell you
where is it that we bring the
probabistic diffusion to this and where
it is we are expanding our research to
and how it came about. First of all, I
showed you a hierarchal system in terms
of community. The fact is that if you
really want to do this for a real
complex system, the number of states and
and the models will be very very
complex. And we know that in active
inferencing one of the issues there is
to compute expected free energy for the
future to define your u you know plans
strategies optimize your strategies
that's an major issue in large complex
systems because computation of these
expected free energies is not easy if
not impossible is not easy. We tried it
for this production system actually this
is a work we are doing in Italy and it's
huge if you are using Mont collar search
all that and creating this habitual
networks and so on in order to calculate
the the expected free energy problem
becomes extremely difficult. So that was
one reason for us to start looking for
maybe different solutions to deal with
expected free energy problem. Now I'm
not going to go through this but I'm
just showing you some of the elements of
how you can use the traditional active
inferencing in terms of Mont color
search and all of it for expected free
energy. But again when you go for large
complex systems these become really big
issues.
So let me just uh stop here for a sec.
What I did was I basically showed you
some examples of real uh complex human
machine systems. I would say I showed
you community. We have done some work in
that you know in that um area. We are
trying to expand our work and really
bring to more uh real
problems. We also did in production
systems um quite complex problem in
terms of state space explosion and so on
so forth. So we have been searching for
some different ways of dealing with with
this expected free energy problem. How
do you really do this? what is the
organic way of really doing it? I feel
that as human we don't do it that way.
We don't search for different solutions
for the future.
Uh active inferencing is really it has
its roots in predictive mind. So to me
it is very organic.
So we we have been trying to find some
organic ways of dealing with expected
free energy. So let me put it that way.
So this brought us to problem
of probabistic
diffusion. What is it? Well, I don't
know if you are familiar Daniel with
probabistic diffusion, but basically the
problem is that you start from initial
data. In this case, image of a
cat.
You bring noise and perturbation to it
until you make a total
noise and then you basically recreate
the image from that. Right? Sounds very
simple. It just happens that when you go
from your initial data in this case
again the image of this cat to total
noise you are basically going through
this marovian uh step and in each step
you have this gshian approximations for
your state variables. Now in this case
your state variables are you know pixels
of the image and you just keep on
applying it to this pixels until you can
create this total noise. So it's fully
corrupted and then you create a reverse
process which is also gshian but then
you have to use some sort of
approximation neural net approximation
or any other sort of approximation to
build the original image the original
data set.
So this has been in the literature I
would say for five six years now. This
is called proistic
diffusion. Looking at it from
engineering perspective I like to call
it reverse engineering because what it
tells me is that I can start from some
ordered structure. I can totally uh
destroy it which is my noise totally
corrupted and then from total disorder I
can recreate order again. Right. So this
is basically what this diffusion is
about. Any questions on this Daniel or
should I continue? Yeah continue. Thank
you.
So without going through the the whole
process of how you do this again this is
a marovian in each step you have uh
gshian uh the assumptions as you're
going forward as you're going backward
again you have gshian it's marovian but
you really have to compute your noise
levels as you're going backward and it
just happens that again there are number
of papers recent papers in the
literature that Going back you can look
at this score function which I have it
here as the gradient of log of Q. Now
one point here when you are going
forward you can assume that you are
using the original distribution even
though you have to approximate it and
when you are going backward you are
trying to get to that original
distribution. So when you are going
forward I have Q I'm using Q for my um
transitions and when I'm going backward
I'm going to introduce some parameter
theta and use P because I want to come
to back to this original distribution
and it just happens that usually
backward reverse or the backward process
you have to use some sort of a neural
net but it is based on this school
function which is gradient of this log
of QT XT given X0. It's a very important
point here. If for my reverse process,
it is important that I keep my original
data set, my original painting
uh accessible because without that
information, this reverse may not be
tractable. Again, we can always go back
to details of it, but this is already in
the literature. There is nothing new on
that one. And the beauty of this
methodology is that you can actually do
sampling, conditional sampling. And by
this conditional sampling, you can
actually define where you want to go
back because you may not actually go
back to the same origin. You may add few
things to it or you may actually change
your original design and that is very
useful when you are looking at reverse
engineering problems.
There is a discrete version of it and to
us this is very interesting because we
think many engineing processes can be
described by graphs and this uh graph
diffusion is is it has been around again
for num few years only few years and
there are number of works on this we are
also trying to use this for engineering
processes
um and the way the you use the graph
diffusion is again you start from a
graph you totally destroy it and then
you build it back. There are some very
interesting applications of this in the
literature. Um in the literature there
are two ways that people have used so
far in terms of using the
diffusion together with reinforcement
learning in control actions. They don't
use active inferencing. They use the
diffusion with reinforcement learning.
Here is one example. This is by a group
from
2022. So basically think about this. You
define your control actions. You have
control actions. You have your states as
I have done here. Like a are your
control actions. S are your states. So
if you comb look at the combination of
actions and states, you have that you
know the small square or rectangle there
and then you put them next to each
other. So you have the whole sequence
going from time zero to whatever time it
is. So if I create this table this looks
more like an image and then of course
actions are states there are
multivariables there are many elements
inside each each. So I have this like a
image type structure and then I apply a
noising and dnoising to it and when I am
going back when I'm doing my reverse
process I can apply reinforcement
learning in terms of some reward
function to find the best sequence of
actions the best trajectories. This is a
very interesting concept and um quite
useful or close to what we are trying to
do. There is another example of this. By
the way, we have taken this methodology
and done some improvement on this
because um when this the the the number
of time steps increases this problem may
not actually uh converge. So we are
looking at some what we call window
stitching and some adaptive planning of
of doing the same thing and we have some
preliminary results on that. Again I'm
not going to go to the details another
work of the similar sort rather than
looking at the actions and states
together they apply the same methodology
to the states and then they use inverse
dynamics to define the actions. Okay,
but pretty much it is the same approach
and with this you can use reinforcement
learning to try to optimize you know
your trajectory.
Now I call these model one these two
model one because they are not actually
using they use reinforcement learning
they have some reward function but they
are not actually formalizing how this
optimization or optimal control should
be. The model two which is our model
actually puts active inferencing and
diffusion
together in the following sense. So
think about it this way. The diffusion
is going to teach me how to go from
point A to point B. Okay? So from
diffusion I can create many different
samples of going from point A to point B
avoiding many obstacles and all of it.
So I already learn how to go from one
point to another point. I look at it as
a predictor. So actually
predistic diffusion creates a motion
prediction for me. Very
organic. And then I can actually use
active inferencing together with this to
find my best sequence of motions going
from one point to another point.
So that is basically the whole um you
know this is the whole theme or whole
the philosophy behind our methodology of
combining active inferencing and
diffusion. So the forward process is the
same as exactly the same as diffusion.
But the backward process every time that
you start from a state in the reverse
process diffusion process you start from
a re you know state and you have again
you have all these different samples of
going from this point to this point. But
for each of them you can apply the
expected free energy from active
inferencing to find which one of them
will give you the best uh sequence of
actions and that is the overall model
that we have here. Let me show you this
in terms of uh let me just jump through
this for a sec
uh to this uh parking model a lot model.
So here suppose I have in the first in
the top graph on the left hand side I
have only uh five six parking slot. In
the other one I have more. So you have
some parked cars. I want to teach these
cars how to go and park themselves in
the best possible way. So there are some
empty slots and these cars starting from
some random place they should go and
park. Okay. So there are two problems
here. One is that first I have to know
how to drive in such an environment
going from point A which is some random
point to a parking slot. That is one
problem. The second problem is that I
have to go to the best slot to the best
place. Right? So what we do is the first
problem we solve it with pro problemic
diffusion. How do I do it? I start
suppose that I take a car, one of these
green cars. I take it from there.
Suppose it is parked in a slot in a
parking lot. I take it from there and I
apply this forward process to it until I
bring it to total noise somewhere out
there. Then I reverse this process and I
create different samples of this reverse
process. So basically by doing so I know
how to start from a how to go from some
random location to a parking lot. So I
have learned that through my diffusion
process. Now that I have that then I
apply my active inferencing to see which
one of them is going to be the my best
choice. One thing here is that as I'm
doing my probabistic diffusion at any
point that I'm look using what I have
learned to find my you know to find my
projection for the future I can use
variational free energy to inject what I
am observing to my diffusion process. So
in a way we are updating our diffusion
process by the observations that I am
actually receiving in real time. Again I
have applied my diffusion. I have set up
samples of how to go from some random
point to a parking spot. I have many
samples but now that I am doing active
inferencing I'm actually applying in
real time. So now I make an observation.
Diffusion tells me go this way it for
the next step it gives me an estimate
but when I actually apply it the result
is a little bit different different. So
I am going to use variational free
energy to make a correction find a new
point and apply my diffusion again until
I get to my best location. So that is
basically the whole idea behind this.
Now in in here the inverse
dynamics is you know bicycle model it's
a very from the literature there's
nothing new about it. So given that I
have my actions or states I can find the
other one. In this example we are
applying the diffusion to the actions
but you can do both again but remember
actions and states are related through
this inverse dynamics model. So that's
not an
issue. One last item here is that really
contribution that we are making here is
actually I would say there are two
contributions. One is how to deal with
expected free energy in really complex
systems in some organic way. That's
number one. And again reverse
engineering is something that we do a
lot in
engineering. Number two is that how to
integrate the elements of active
inferencing especially with the
variational free energy to update my
diffusion process. And in this work that
we did for the parking model, we were
actually able to to to demonstrate that
uh before getting into any and maybe
Yuling can help me here. Now we are
trying to use this idea for many
different applications and we are also
trying to expand our parking model to
more navigation on the road by looking
at stitching this windows together. And
one of the areas that we are trying to
work on is how to actually navigate a
ball for example on a table which is
very dynamic. So it is tilting there are
frictions and it has to be able to find
its way. So we are thinking that this
ball is looking for food but we don't
know if there is a food or not. So the
ball has to go or this this organism has
to go and find has to survive but in
order to survive it has to find food but
it doesn't know if there is a food. So
it has to explore this in a very dynamic
environment. And again you is there
anything you want to mention here before
we
start come our conversation about all
this. Yuling are you there?
Well,
can you can you can you say a few words
on this unit? Sorry, uh I just lost
audio for a second. Um sure. Um so this
is the most recent work we're doing. Um
so again as Dr. Jafar described um this
is similar to um team Snider Dr.
Snider's work about active exploration
for robotic manipulations right and as
as duter described this environment is
extremely challenging and almost
impossible for reinforcement learning
and we add extra layer of challenge just
um tutting the table such that that the
table is dynamic during the learning
explosion task.
So our my our idea is to solve this
problem with a hierarchical setting
right. So
um right now we're experimenting with
three layers. So the the top layer is a
high level planner um as a active
inference using active inference. So
using active inference controller this
layer updates belief using variational
free energy and performance planning
using the expected free energy. So where
does the expected free energy all those
information comes? Um we need to sample
many different possible trajectories
right. So that's how we move to the uh
the the second layer the diffusion
projector. Um our diffusion projector
learns from from data set and from past
experience to generate possible paths.
The high level active inference layer um
we select a preferred region right uh
some kind of points or area or
distribution as we refer to G
distribution.
That belief gets passed on to the
diffusion planner and the diffusion
planner generate many possible
trajectories to that region. And at this
point the actual goal uh hasn't been fun
yet. We are still looking for the goal
but we are generating diverse trajectory
towards that most uh probable region
right and these trajectories consist of
a sequence of way points and
corresponding states that um represent
the possible p possible path. Um and
then obviously we calculate the expected
free energy and then select the best
possible trajectory. And once we have
the trajectory, now we have the
low-level controller, right? The
low-level controller um is just a
lightweight small scale reinforcement
learning controller that generate
actions to connect the small way points.
So by having this hierarchical
structure, uh we believe we can solve
this problem um much faster than the
original literature um where Dr. Snider
solved this problem with model
predictive control uh with active
inference. Um if you run that it takes
tremendous amounts of planning time and
learning time and we believe by because
of the nature of diffusion process we
can make this learning process and
planning process much faster.
Thank
you. Well Daniel I think we are done.
Sorry I don't know how long it took but
it was long. I'm sorry.
Oh, it was awesome. Yeah, I'll ask some
questions. Questions.
Is that okay? Is that okay? Yes. Well, I
think there's some sort of
back echo. I know. I think it might be
on your side.
Oh,
it sounds cool though. Sounds cool
though.
Okay.
But is there any way to like maybe mute?
It's It's minimal when you're talking.
Oh, it it's
okay. Okay. Um All right. I'll read some
of the presubmitted questions. Some of
them are cool to maybe get your uh short
short takes on. So, should I should I
keep the should I share or should I just
You can keep it up and I'll it's it's
Yeah, you can keep it up and I'll just
if in case you want to show a slide. um
how did you incorporate physics like
friction forces or air resistance into
the model? So when you're and and just
thinking from your engineering expertise
more broadly, how do you bring in these
physical features and constraints into
the the model's dynamics to what extent
do you encode them symbolically
um coarse grain them? How do you include
those in the model?
Well, again there are two aspects of the
model here. So let me just go
back. One thing I want to make sure that
we are on the same page. There are two
thing we are looking at. One is this
hierarchal models right large complex
hierarchal models. And one example is
here. This is one example. This is
physics. This is to I mean this is a
time series model from from the
temperature in a zone and uh in this in
this case for a given zone we have this
type of phys physics model right and and
it is easy to incorporate it both in
terms of states and actions and so on.
But in all honesty when you enlarge the
system, if you look at the complex
zones, if you look at many different
factors,
uh it would be very difficult to find a
physics based
uh tractable model to actually
to use in which case you have to use
some sort of neural nets or some sort of
approximation. So this is one example
where you bring physics. Another example
which I showed you is is um
here where
um this is it. This is the bicycle
model. Again this comes from physics in
terms of doing the inverse
dynamics kinematics. So
um I think that's a great question. We
have done some of it. I don't know the
answer to all of it. How it is going to
be done, how it can be done. But
depending on the system, I think it is
very possible to incorporate physics. Uh
but again when the system becomes
complex, it may not be very tractable.
Yeah. Sorry. Sorry. Just add a small
point to that. Um so in training the
diffusion model we are using the data
from the physical simulation. So um I
think that was incorporate as a noise to
the physical simulation where the
diffusion model learns from
data frictions uh and the and the
physical
properties and that was very good point
Julen because there is another point for
example when you are training it for
buildings for instance you use some
digital twin of the building right and
for that again that digital twin
incorporates is many of the physics
elements of that building in the back
end not directly using the active
inferencing or diffusion but in the back
end it is using it. So there are
different ways of using physics but
again assuming that it is
tractable. Awesome. How did you handle
perception through sensors and sensor
fusion and feature extraction of the
data from these sensors? So how do you
do structure learning on uh everything
from which of the kind of layers of the
system to model on through which kinds
of model architectures you used for the
uh neural network mediated
steps. Well let's step back on it. So if
you are looking at from active
influencing perspective well if you have
a continuous systems then again you look
at the dynamics continuous dynamics of
the system. If it is too complex of
course you use this probabistic
framework to describe it. If it is
discrete more than likely you are using
some sort of a markov or state
transition behavior. So having said that
let me just go back to this. I'm glad
that first of all let me also stop here.
There are many engineering systems that
can be described by
graphs. Uh perhaps you can call them
automata in terms of the if you look at
it from computer science perspective but
the graph models are very usual. But let
me go back to this to answer to that
question. And I'm glad that I have that
slide in here. Um actually I kept that
side looking at the questions that you
have. This is one good example of how I
can use the sensor information. So if
I'm looking looking at these tables you
can think about lambda. So think about
it this way that you define a time a
time unit and again I'm talking very
engineering define a time unit 1 second
2 seconds 5 seconds whatever
milliseconds and if you don't receive
any information or any data you call it
lambda t arrow up could be that
temperature is going up arrow down means
temperature is coming up coming down and
so on so forth the same for the P
pressure and so on so basically what you
see on this table that's a process data.
These are actual data you're receiving
from the process. But there is a
methodology that you can take this and
from that you can create the automat or
the state transition graph on the on the
right hand side and as this sensor
information or data is increasing and
becoming more and more you can keep on
uh updating your model. So there are
already ways of creating this type of
structures. Now again in active
inferencing the underlying assumption is
that if you are using a discrete model
it is some sort of a state transition
diagram okay you use markup blankets or
you use state transition diagrams and
there are ways to build it I mean it's
not we have done a lot of work on this
in the past this is an existing work in
the literature for almost from 20 years
ago so there are ways to build that but
when you come to the active influence
ing or diffusion you already assume that
you have that
structure. Okay. So to us it's not part
of active inferencing. Active
inferencing you already have it in
there. But again of course you can
combine all of them together.
Yeah, that was a really interesting
angle with uh the noising process as
sequential. Sorry, I'm
I'm getting a little bit of an echo from
you still. So could you just mute?
Okay. Thank you. Thank you. Yeah. The
sequential application of the Gaussian
process which also has kind of analogy
in if you're 90% confident each time
step then there's a decay in the
confidence. So it's kind of like
projecting out through time and then
planning backwards in time with
increasing precision is like moving
forward in reducing uncertainty about a
path to take in a planning space but it
was the other direction from a
diffusive information
uh neutralizing direction. And so it's a
it's a um algorithmic way to kind of
talk about the forward and the
backwards aspect of gaining and removing
information and um how do you plug this
into existing engineering tools or what
kinds of toolkits are you using for
specifying and for running these models?
[Music]
unmute.
Two models that we have tried so far.
One is that parking lot model in a
simulated environment. We have created a
simulated environment for it. Uh we are
planning to expand it of course and uh
so that is one model and and and again
the diffusion there as you said it is a
it's a it's a predictor. It predicts and
first it uh by going forward it tries to
uh lose information totally and then by
going uh backward it tries to gain the
information and by doing so it finds the
its way of how to go from one random
location in this parking area whatever
that is to a to a to a specific um you
know parking spot. And uh by doing so uh
then you you use this into your
optimization because you want to find
which spot is really your best spot and
you have to go and park there. Um
honestly it is it it it is so organic in
engineering system because the
engineering system work like this in
engineering system you always have some
organic if you look at it human
humanlike systems and that is why I'm so
interested in active inferencing because
it's so organic we always do it that way
you always have a process defined okay
there is always a structure and you want
to always use that structure to find the
solution. So to me it is very organic in
engineering like systems and as I said
many engineering systems you can use
graphs to describe them. Many
engineering systems are hierarchal. You
can decompose it and look at the you
know simpler cases. You can create
abstractions. But to me it is very
natural that you organically learn how
to do things and then you use your
expertise to find the best way of doing
it. You don't mix the two. you basic
well you you integrate the two but you
understand that first you have to know
how to build one piece but then you
think about okay how am I going to
optimize this so you use that knowledge
to optimize it and that's exactly what
we are trying to
do awesome all right in closing just
give your thoughts on this it'll be
awesome and and thanks again for this
great work so what would be the
obstacles to advancing this approach to
more complex autonomous navigation
scenarios and agents.
Well, honestly, I don't know this
may again see there are two elements
here. One is the diffusion or the
projector and the other one is the
optimizer which is active inferencing.
So, we have a projector, we have an
optimizer. These two are integrated
together.
I'm sure there will be complexities and
you know this as we move on in this
direction I'm sure we will find many
complexities but see let's just look at
the the projector the projector which is
a
diffusion it has to um I forgot to say
that the two examples I showed you on
the diffusion from the literature they
both assume that the initial data sample
is uh there there is an expert so there
is some expert information sitting there
meaning that on the driving in the
parking lot example I already know where
I should be going I am expert in going
from one point to a parking spot we
don't want to make that assumption we
are looking at cases that there is no
expert information on this so you really
have to learn from almost nothing when
you do it that way then you have to
somehow find ways of doing a lot of
sampling. Well, the sampling with
diffusion is much much easier than and
much more efficient than doing Monte
Carlo searches. Much much easier than
that. But still you have to create that
type of knowledge base and then you use
that knowledge base in your
optimization. So I personally think that
that may be a an area that needs some
attention. And the second area is of
course the complexity of active
inferencing in engineering system itself
because you know engineering systems are
big. It's huge. I mean if you want to
look at real applications you're really
looking at large systems. I mean a
production system there may be hundreds
thousands of machines and processes that
you have to integrate all together. How
do you incorporate all this into this
fusion diffusion and active influencing
framework? Well, remains to be seen but
definitely very interesting problem.
Awesome. You do you have any last words
or or what what stage are you in where
you going? Where are you going with
that? Well, uh just to answer your last
question, um I think the biggest
challenging is growing state space,
right? If you if the problem if the like
the driving navigation problem gets
extremely complex if we introduce a
bigger map then space space space a
state space will just
explode it will introduce a very big
computational challenge. That's why we
want to use diffusion and we want to use
the window station method to separate a
big problem into a smaller problems.
Awesome. Awesome.
Thank you again for joining. Looking
forward to hearing more about this work
in due time.
Thank you so much. Thank you. Thanks so
much. Bye-bye. Bye-bye. Bye.